<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: twitter | IFHO]]></title>
  <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/categories/twitter/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-28T17:09:16+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://gurgeh.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Fendrich]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milliblogging - An essay in 7 tweets]]></title>
    <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/2010/08/19/milliblogging-essae-in-7-tweets/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/2010/08/19/milliblogging-essae-in-7-tweets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Twitter became popular because of its 140 character restriction, orginally designed to fit an SMS.<br /><br />This restriction promises the follower that everything will be easily digested, but perhaps more important is the benefit to the writer.<br /><br />Often someone starts a blog, but then quits when every post becomes too long. Too ambitious. Twitter frees the writer of such pressure.<br /><br />Pressure to be concise is great, but I propose that the 140 char limit is too limiting to express anything interesting. Tweets are dumb.<br /><br />Instead of microblogging, I propose #milliblogging. You must constrict yourself to (maybe?) 1000 characters - the length of 7 tweets.<br /><br />Would you join such a site? Would you rather it be an extended Twitter-client or a new community?<br /><br />#Milliblogging - for people with something to say.<br /><br />(This post was also tweeted by me on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/fnedrik">http://www.twitter.com/fnedrik</a> )</div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Daivd</div>
<div class='content'>
I started out with the target of 5 tweets / 700 characters, but I found out that to express the idea itself, I needed 7 tweets.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>RBerenguel</div>
<div class='content'>
Interesting idea. I don&#39;t know. Usually my posts are way long... Maybe I can try to write my next post as 7 tweets to try.<br /><br />Ruben</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
