<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: optopus | IFHO]]></title>
  <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/categories/optopus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-28T16:57:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://gurgeh.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Fendrich]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solving Sudoku with genetic algorithms]]></title>
    <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/2010/05/05/solving-sudoku-with-genetic-algorithms/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/2010/05/05/solving-sudoku-with-genetic-algorithms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I recently wrote a small Python library for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_algorithm">genetic algorithms</a> (GA), called <a href="http://code.google.com/p/optopus">optopus</a>. One thing I tried when I played around with it was to solve a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudoku">Sudoku</a> puzzle. There are plenty of efficient ways to solve Sudoku, but with my shiny new hammer, all problems look like nails.<br /><br />Also, I remember that I once read something from someone who tried a GA C-library on Sudoku and concluded that it was not a suitable problem. If I could solve it with my slick library, that random person on the internet, whose web page I might never find again but who may exist as far as you know, would certainly be proven wrong. A worthy cause.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-large;">Genetic algorithms</span><br />A genetic algorithm is a general way to solve optimization problems. The basic algorithm is very simple:<br /><ol><li>Create a population (vector) of random solutions (represented in a problem specific way, but often a vector of floats or ints)</li><li>Pick a few solutions and sort them according to fitness</li><li>Replace the worst solution with a new solution, which is either&nbsp;a copy of the best solution, a mutation (perturbation) of the best&nbsp;solution, an entirely new randomized solution or a cross between the two&nbsp;best solutions. These are the most common evolutionary operators, but you could dream up others that use information from existing solutions to create new potentially good solutions.</li><li>Check if you have a new global best fitness, if so, store the solution.</li><li>If too many iterations go by without improvement, the entire population&nbsp;might be stuck in a local minimum (at the bottom of a local valley, with a possible chasm&nbsp;somewhere else, so to speak). If so, kill everyone and start over at 1.</li><li>Go to 2.</li></ol>Fitness is a measure of how good a solution is, lower meaning better. This measure is performed by a fitness function that you supply. Writing a fitness function is how you describe the problem to the GA. The magnitude of the fitness values returned does not matter (in sane implementations), only how they compare to each other.<br /><br />There are other, subtly different, ways to perform the evolutionary process. Some are good and some are popular but bad. The one described above is called tournament selection and it is one of the good ways. Much can be said about the intricacies of GA but it will have to be said somewhere else, lest I digress completely.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-large;">Optopus and Sudoku</span><br />Using optopus is easy:<br /><br /><pre class="brush: python">from optopus import ga, stdgenomes<br /><br />#Now we choose a representation. We know that the answer to the puzzle must be some permutation of the digits 1 to 9, each used nine times.<br /><br />init_vect = sum([range(1,10)] * 9, []) # A vector of 81 elements<br />genome = stdgenomes.PermutateGenome (init_vect)<br /><br />#I made a few functions to calculate how many conflicts a potential Sudoku solution has. I'll show them later, but for now let us just import the package. I also found a puzzle somewhere and put it in the PUZZLE constant.<br /><br />import sudoku<br />solver = ga.GA(sudoku.ga_sudoku(sudoku.PUZZLE) , genome)<br /><br />#And now, when we have supplied the GA with a fitness function (ga_sudoku, which counts Sudoku conflicts) and a representation (genome), let us just let the solver do its magic.<br /><br />solver.evolve(target_fitness=0)<br /></pre><br />And in a few minutes (about 2.6 million iterations when I tried) the correct answer pops out!<br /><br />The nice thing about this method is that you do not have to know anything about how to solve a Sudoku puzzle or even think very hard at all. Note that I did not even bother to just let it search for the unknown values - it also has to find the digits that we already know (which should not be too hard with a decent fitness function, see below). The only bit of thinking we did was to understand that a Sudoku solution has to be a permutation of&nbsp;<i>[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]</i>, but this merely made the evolution part faster. If we wanted to make it faster still, we could make a genome type that let us say that there are actually nine separate vectors who are each guaranteed to be a permutation of 1 to 9. We could have thought even less and represented the solution by 81 ints who are all in the range 1 to 9, by using another genome type:<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;">&gt;&gt; genome = stdgenomes.EnumGenome(81, range(1,10))</span></span><br /><br />The range argument to EnumGenome does not have to be a vector of integers, it could be a vector of any objects, since they are never treated like numbers.<br /><br />In my experiment this took maybe 15 - 30 minutes to solve. For more difficult Sudoku puzzles, I would definitely go with the permutation genome, since using EnumGenome increases the search space to 9^81 or <i>196627050475552913618075908526912116283103450944214766927315415537966391196809</i> possible solutions.<br /><br />FYI, this is the puzzle in sudoku.PUZZLE:<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>&nbsp;&nbsp;4|8 &nbsp;| 17</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>67 |9 &nbsp;| &nbsp;&nbsp;</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>5 8| 3 | &nbsp;4</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>-----------</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>3 &nbsp;|74 |1 &nbsp;</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>&nbsp;69| &nbsp; |78&nbsp;</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>&nbsp;&nbsp;1| 69| &nbsp;5</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>-----------</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>1 &nbsp;| 8 |3 6</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>&nbsp;&nbsp; | &nbsp;6| 91</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><b>24 | &nbsp;1|5 &nbsp;</b></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><br /></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;">I think a Sudoku puzzle that is harder for humans would not be that much harder for optopus to solve, but I have not tested it.</span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><br /></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-large;">Sudoku fitness function</span></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;">OK, so that was a ridiculously easy way to solve a Sudoku puzzle, but I skipped one part that is crucial to all GA - describing the problem using a fitness function. I had to do the following:</span><br /><br /><pre class="brush: python">DIM = 9<br /><br />def one_box(solution, i):<br />    """Extract the 9 elements of a 3 x 3 box in a 9 x 9 Sudoku solution."""<br />    return solution[i:i+3] + solution[i+9:i+12] + solution[i+18:i+21]<br /><br />def boxes(solution):<br />    """Divide a flat vector into vectors with 9 elements, representing 3 x 3<br />    boxes in the corresponding 9 x 9 2D vector. These are the standard<br />    Sudoku boxes."""<br />    return [one_box(solution, i) for i in [0, 3, 6, 27, 30, 33, 54, 57, 60]]<br /><br />def splitup(solution):<br />    """Take a flat vector and make it 2D"""<br />    return [solution[i * DIM:(i + 1) * DIM] for i in xrange(DIM)]<br /><br />def consistent(solution):<br />    """Check how many different elements there are in each row.<br />    Ideally there should be DIM different elements, if there are no duplicates."""<br />    return sum(DIM - len(set(row)) for row in solution)<br /><br />def compare(xs1, xs2):<br />    """Compare two flat vectors and return how much they differ"""<br />    return sum(1 if x1 and x1 != x2 else 0 for x1, x2 in zip(xs1, xs2))<br /><br />def sudoku_fitness(flatsolution, puzzle, flatpuzzle=None):<br />    """Evaluate the fitness of flatsolution."""<br />    if not flatpuzzle:<br />        flatpuzzle = sum(puzzle, [])<br />    solution = splitup(flatsolution)<br />    fitness = consistent(solution) #check rows<br />    fitness += consistent(zip(*solution)) #check columns<br />    fitness += consistent(boxes(flatsolution)) #check boxes<br />    fitness += compare(flatpuzzle, flatsolution) * 10 #check that it matches the known digits<br />    return fitness<br /><br />def ga_sudoku(puzzle):<br />    """Return a fitness function wrapper that extracts the .genes attribute from<br />    an individual and sends it to sudoku_fitness."""<br />    flatpuzzle = sum(puzzle, []) #just a precalcing optimization<br />    def fit(guy):<br />        return sudoku_fitness(guy.genes, puzzle, flatpuzzle)<br />    return fit<br /></pre><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"><br /></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;">I know. This made the solution less clean. Still, I made it verbose for readability, so it is perhaps less code than it looks.</span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;"><br /></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;">Take that, random internet guy!</span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: inherit;"><br /></span></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Daivd</div>
<div class='content'>
@blob Unfortunately I have no variable length genomes in optopus, but it is easy enough to create one yourself. Look at BaseGenome and perhaps take some inspiration from FloatGenome.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>blob</div>
<div class='content'>
Is there a built-in Genome that allows for a variable number of objects?<br /><br />Thanks! (:</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Stefaan</div>
<div class='content'>
I coded a Java GA for solving sudoku this year in a Meta-Heuristics course I took post grad. The best solving time I obtained from a few runs of AL Escargot was 9 minutes 41 seconds on a 2.66ghz core2 workstation, other problems took from sub one to 40 odd seconds depending on the difficulty. In the end the GA used four different methods of applying selection pressure, 4 more methods to then pare up parents, six different crossover methods, a modified island model and population restarting conditions... Needless to say comparitively to other meta-heuristics it is a very inefficient method.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Cleve</div>
<div class='content'>
Human puzzle solvers and computers use very different approaches for Sudoku.  Humans are good at finding patterns.  Computers use brute force with genetic algorithms or other forms of recursive backtracking.  Take a look at:<br />   http://www.mathworks.com/moler/exm/chapters/sudoku.pdf</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jerren</div>
<div class='content'>
So there is a GA to solve Sudoku.  That means there must be a constructive algorithm to solve it too.<br />What is the constructive algorithm?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>StartBreakingFree.com</div>
<div class='content'>
Pretty cool, so did it solve one sudoku puzzle or did it evolve an algorithm to solve sudoku puzzles in general?<br /><br />Thanks for posting it!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>micks</div>
<div class='content'>
Very interesting way to solve sudoku.<br /><br />I am just curious, exactly how long did it take for you to solve Sudoku? <br />I have a solution that solves Sudoku (among other tougher problems) very fast. <br />I just want to know your number before telling(bragging, as some might say) about mine.<br /><br />I just wanna compare the speed of the two solutions, yours and mine.<br />Really good post.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>vaevictus-net</div>
<div class='content'>
Seems like genetic algorithms for sudoku solutions are a decent example of GA.  But I think it might be fun/interesting to use GA to build some sort of logic engine to solve sudokus.  :)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Daivd</div>
<div class='content'>
@albert<br /><br />I agree, that is a good approach.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>albert</div>
<div class='content'>
This is better:<br />http://norvig.com/sudoku.html</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Doug</div>
<div class='content'>
Damn, This is mind numbing good...</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gates in practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/2010/04/27/gates-in-practice/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://gurgeh.github.com/blog/2010/04/27/gates-in-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Remember the classification problem from <a href="http://fakeguido.blogspot.com/2010/04/confident-optimization-using-gates.html">part 1</a>? I wrote a small script to simulate solutions with different success rates.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">For our first investigation, let us say that we have created 600 solutions. 400 of them have a true fitness 0.5 (a 50% chance to answer correctly - no better than random since our test cases are 50/50 positive and negative) and 200 of them have found something and have a true fitness of 0.6. One limitation to these simulations is that we assume that two different solutions with a fitness of 0.6 are totally uncorrelated on the tests, while in reality the solutions might very well have picked up on the same pattern and be completely correlated.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">In our hypothetical situation we have 300 different test cases that are out of sample, i.e not used by the process that created the solutions.300 test cases might seem like very few, but the circumstances are favorable. The 50/50 split between positive and negative helps. If it was just one positive in a hundred, many more cases would be needed. If the test cases are weighted, with some more important than others to get right, you also need more test cases.</div><div><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Running the 600 solutions through the 300 test cases, we might get the following histogram with 15 bins:</div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9VX31h9Q7I/AAAAAAAAAEA/6fYx09jTTRw/s1600/Gate+histogram+for+peaks.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="482" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9VX31h9Q7I/AAAAAAAAAEA/6fYx09jTTRw/s640/Gate+histogram+for+peaks.png" width="640" /></a></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">If we could measure the fitness exactly, we would just see two bars - one at 0.5 and one at 0.6. Based on this graph, can we take the best solution and ask what is the probability that it is better than 0.55? 0.58? 0.62? It is hard to know. It really looks like there ought to be some solution better than 0.6.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">I divided the 300 tests into three gates with 100 in each. In some of my tests, no solution made it through all the gates, suggesting that I either needed more tests or more solutions, so just to test the theory I increased the number of 0.5-solutions to 100 000 and 0.6 to 50 000.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Running the solutions through the gates with a cutoff of 0.55 (meaning that we search for solutions that have a true fitness of 0.55 or better and only let those through that have a measured fitness of 0.55 on each gate) yielded the following result:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C0 = 150000</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C1 = 54774 (C0 / C1 = 2.74)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C2 = 35543 (C1 / C2 = 1.54)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C2 = 27891 (C2 / C3 = 1.27)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">The ratios are decreasing nicely, as expected. I solved the equations in part 1 numerically, using my genetic algorithm library,&nbsp;<a href="http://code.google.com/p/optopus">optopus</a>, for Python, thus ending up with the following:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.34 good solutions, with 0.82 passing through each gate</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.66 bad solutions, with 0.14 passing through each gate</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">This means that the predicted probability of drawing a good solution after each gate is:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.34 (before any gate. True value is approx. 0.33)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.75 (after one gate. True 0.75)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.95 (0.95)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.99 (0.99)</i></div><br /><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">So in this particular special case, our method gets exactly the correct answer!</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Let us make it slightly harder and choose a cutoff that is not exactly in the middle between 0.5 and 0.6.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Running the solutions as above with cutoff 0.58 (we now ask how many are equal to or better than 0.58) yielded this:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C0 = 150000</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C1 = 35450 (C0 / C1 = 4.13)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C2 = 19571 (C1 / C2 = 1.81)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C2 = 11994 (C2 / C3 = 1.63)</i></div><br /><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Once again we get a nice decreasing ratio. Solving it numerically gets us these parameters</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.34 good solutions, with 0.62 passing through each gate</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.66 bad solutions with 0.04 passing through each gate</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">and these predicted probabilities of drawing a good solution after each gate:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.34 (True: 0.33)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.88 (0.88)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.99 (0.99)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.999 (0.999)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Ridiculously good!</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Let us make it harder still and pick a cutoff above the top solutions. This violates the assumption in part 1, that we have at least one good solution.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">With cutoff 0.62, I got this:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C0 = 150000</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C1 = 16043 (C0 / C1 = 9.35)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C2 = 4733 (C1 / C2 = 3.39)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C3 = 1400 (C2 / C1 = 3.38)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Here something worrisome happens. The ratio stops decreasing. Since this ratio is supposed to asymptotically reach the inverse of Pg, the probability that a good solution pass the gate, this should trigger an alarm. If we say that the fitness of a good solution has to be better than or equal to 0.62 and have a cutoff of 0.62 in the gates, how can only one in 3.38 pass? We should always get at least half of the good solutions through.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Running the GA gives:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.35 good, with a 0.3 probability to pass</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.65 bad with a 0.0004 probability to pass</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Which is completely wrong, since there are only bad solutions if we try to find solutions that are 0.62 or better. Remember that all our solutions have a true fitness of 0.5 or 0.6. We again get a stern warning that something is wrong, since a 0.3 probability to pass is too low. We expect at least half of the good solutions to pass. More than half should pass if the solutions are noticeably above the cutoff value, but anything under 0.5 means we are in trouble.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Taking that warning into account, it would seem that the gate test worked here as well.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-large;">The problem</span></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Does it always work? Sadly, no. As I hinted in my last post, there is a problem. Let us say that instead of two kinds of solutions, 0.5 and 0.6, we have 100 solutions distributed evenly between 0.3 and 0.7. Just sending this solution distribution through the 300 tests yields (15 bins):</div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9VX8HlcdWI/AAAAAAAAAEI/pcuKNok-R6s/s1600/Gate+histogram+for+even+dist.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="482" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9VX8HlcdWI/AAAAAAAAAEI/pcuKNok-R6s/s640/Gate+histogram+for+even+dist.png" width="640" /></a></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">The distribution does not look very uniform anymore, but at least it looks like we have nothing over 0.7, which is true.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">With cutoff 0.65, we get:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C0 = 40000</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C1 = 4656 (C0 / C1 = 8.59)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C2 = 2385 (C1 / C2 = 1.95)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>C3 = 1392 (C2 / C1 = 1.71)</i></div><div><br /></div><div>Everything looks all right. Running the GA gives:</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.17 good, with a 0.58 probability to pass</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.83 bad with a 0.18 probability to pass</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><br /><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.17 (True: 0.13)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.87 (0.68)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.99 (0.85)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><i>0.999 (0.93)</i></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">As can be seen, the algorithm overestimates how many good solutions there are. This happens because one of our initial assumptions, that there are only either good or bad solutions, is wrong. Since the C-ratios decrease, it looks like we get progressively more and more good solutions, which we are, but at a smaller rate than indicated. What happens is that the better a solution is, the more likely it is to survive, so the gates make sure that the better of the bad solutions survive, which makes a larger ratio of the entire "population" of solutions survive each time.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Note that the answer will not always be overestimated. If the even distribution is located mainly to the right of the cutoff, I think that the answer will instead be underestimated, but I have not yet tested this. It might be worth mentioning that running with cutoff 0.72 yielded very bad C-ratios, so that still works as before.</div><br /><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-large;">Gates as transfer functions</span></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">A series of test cases and a cutoff value can be seen as a transfer function on the distribution of solutions. When the solutions are run through a gate, the transfer function is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convolve">convolved</a>&nbsp;with the solution distribution to yield a new solution distribution. In the graph below, I have plotted the transfer functions for five different gates, with the same cutoff but with different number of test cases. Once again we have relatively few test cases, but just as we discussed earlier, if the test cases are not divided 50/50 between positive and negative or there are weights, we need many more to get the same gate characteristics.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9WV3GVHcHI/AAAAAAAAAEg/aJI4ZFzcr7c/s1600/Gate+Transfer+Functions+70.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="482" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9WV3GVHcHI/AAAAAAAAAEg/aJI4ZFzcr7c/s640/Gate+Transfer+Functions+70.png" width="640" /></a></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">The more test cases that the gate has, the steeper the transfer function. It will look more and more like a step function as the gate gets "larger". In the limit that is actually is a step function (with infinitely many test cases), our earlier assumption fully holds and the predictions would again be correct. These transfer functions will move the solution distribution to the right (better true fitness). The only thing we can measure is still C, the number of solutions left, which in the continuous case would be the integral of the solution distribution.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-large;">Possible solutions</span></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">If we knew the shape of our initial solution distribution and the shape of the transfer function, we would once again be in business and be able to predict the number of solutions above a cutoff correctly. The transfer function can be estimated, but the solution distribution can vary greatly. Maybe all solutions have the same true fitness? Maybe they are divided into two "pillars" as in the example above? Maybe they are spread in some more complex shape across the spectrum?</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Instead of just finding out the value of two points of the solution distribution (good and bad), we would get better estimates if we could get the value of more points. But knowledge of more variables require more equations. Where will these equations come from? We have two sources of untapped information.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">First of all, we have not used the exact result when the solutions are run against the test, only if they pass the cutoff or not. By letting the cutoff move from 0 to 1 and running the same gates over and over again, we can gain additional information on the shape of the solution distribution. If the transfer functions where linear, we would not gain additional information from this, but since they are not, the different resulting integrals can tell us something.</div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9VX_cQzHlI/AAAAAAAAAEY/AJtkYerEHtc/s1600/Gate+Transfer+Functions+with+9+Test+Cases.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="482" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_-8MSZS6yWdk/S9VX_cQzHlI/AAAAAAAAAEY/AJtkYerEHtc/s640/Gate+Transfer+Functions+with+9+Test+Cases.png" width="640" /></a></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">The results of the different cutoffs are of course not totally independent, so each new cutoff will not magically bring about a new independent equation, but it will still improve our understanding of the shape of the solution distribution.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">The other source of information that we have not used is that not all solutions run against all test cases, since we filter out so many after each gate. This means that there are tests (thus information) that are not being used. The easiest way to use this information is to do as suggested in <a href="http://fakeguido.blogspot.com/2010/04/confident-optimization-using-gates.html">part 1</a>&nbsp;and rerun the gate experiment with the gates in different order. This will not give more equations, but will increase the accuracy of the measured Cs which in turn may allow more gates with fewer tests in each, which gives more equations.</div><br /><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">This is my main approach and the one that I will test in practice and write my next post about.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">I have, however, two other rough ideas that one could pursue.</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">One approach is to abandon gates and look at the measured fitness histogram for all test cases (like the two I have shown above) and try to run it in reverse, by generating hypothetical true distributions and see how likely they are to end up in the measured distribution after the blurring effect of the test process. Maybe image deblurring techniques such as Gaussian&nbsp;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noise_reduction">noise reduction</a>&nbsp;can be used?</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">The other approach is to study&nbsp;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deconvolution">deconvolution</a>&nbsp;- the process of running a convolution in reverse. According to the Wikipedia article, deconvolution is often associated with image processing, where it is used to reverse optical distortion. Maybe this method will actually converge with the deblurring approach?</div><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"><br /></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
