<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: planning | IFHO]]></title>
  <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/categories/planning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fendrich.se/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-26T14:45:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://fendrich.se/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Fendrich]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why planning is hard]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/21/why-planning-is-hard/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/21/why-planning-is-hard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
After my last post about planning I thought some more on the issue and had something close to an epiphany.<br /><br />When you plan, in the solitaire sense, you need rules governing what moves are legal - transformation rules. If you treat these rules like black boxes, just understanding them by playing around with positions and see how they behave, you can only do so much. An important rule might be usable extremely rarely, but nevertheless be the key to success if you specifically aim to reach a position where it is applicable. This means that you might miss how important a rule (or an exception to a rule) is, when just "black-boxing" it, because it's usefulness or purpose might never come up.<br /><br />Even if you have no such rare rules in your system, the best you can hope for if you want to analyze a system when black-boxing is just to formulate your own internal rules for how the system seems to behave.<br /><br />Thus, <span style="font-weight: bold;">the reason planning is hard is that you need to be able to analyze/understand code to understand transformation rules in general</span> and understanding code is hard. You need to understand when you may take actions and what these actions do, i.e understand transformation rules, whatever system you are planning for.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">A small prediction<br /><br /></span>The reason why good planning is a key to analyze code and prove things in formal systems is that you need to understand code in order to plan. Thus, I postulate, when something can analyze code better than I, it will quickly learn to do everything else intelligence-based better than I. The implication probably works both ways, so the first program that is thoroughly smarter than I will most likely have it's foundation laid upon the ability to reason about code.</div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Home Broker</div>
<div class='content'>
Hello. This post is likeable, and your blog is very interesting, congratulations :-). I will add in my blogroll =). If possible gives a last there on my blog, it is about the <A HREF="http://home-broker-brasil.blogspot.com" REL="nofollow">Home Broker</A>, I hope you enjoy. The address is http://home-broker-brasil.blogspot.com. A hug.<A HREF="8250556117" REL="nofollow"></A></div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deceptively simple game]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/12/deceptively-simple-game/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/12/deceptively-simple-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I would pay a handsome sum (say $1 million, if I could raise it) for a program that could do the following well-defined, seemingly simple, task.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">General solitaire solver</span><br /><br />Take as input a list of rules for a solitaire-like game. The rules are deterministic transformation rules, defining which moves are legal given a certain position. The rules will be given in whatever Turing complete language the solver likes. For example a simple Scheme dialect without side-effects or a subset of x86 machine code.<br /><br />As long as it solves the task, the solver is free to treat the rules as <span style="font-style: italic;">black boxes</span> that take one position and outputs a, possibly empty, list of potential positions.<br /><br />The solver will then take an initial position as second input and one or more target positions as final input. In fact, to make it more general, take a function that tells whether a position is the target or not.<br /><br />As output, I want a sequence of transformations that leads from the initial position to a target. It does not have to be the shortest sequence, just a sequence. Also I want the answer reasonably fast. At least as fast as I could solve it myself.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Extra features</span><br /><br />While I would be very happy with just the above, here are some extra features that would be nice.<br /><br /><ul><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Instead of a binary target function, let me use a continuous target function, and give as output a sequence that gives an end position with as good a score as possible.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Accept one or more opponents. This would be useful for playing games - go, shogi, chess, etc, but apart from that would probably be a step towards the stochastic thing below.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Allow the transformation rules to behave in a stochastic/probabilistic manner.</span></li></ul><span style="font-size:130%;">Why?</span><br /><br />I have no particular desire to solve solitaire automatically, so why would I want a generalized solitaire solver? Well, if you can input the rules for solitaire, you can also input the rules for <a href="http://seedai.blogspot.com/search/label/Towers%20of%20Hanoi">Towers of Hanoi</a>, which I used as an example of difficult planning in another post. Suddenly you can solve a whole range of reasoning problems, mathematical proofs, reasoning about programs and all sorts of interesting and important stuff.<br /><br />It is interesting to think about the problem from the point of view of solving solitaire or some other simple one-man game. I think it makes it less intimidating.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seed AI]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/08/30/seed-ai/"/>
    <updated>2007-08-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/08/30/seed-ai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<span style="font-size:130%;">Le grand assumption<br /><br /></span>The assumption of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seed_AI">seed AI</a> is this: <blockquote>If we can make a program intelligent enough, a "seed" of intelligence, we can also make it gradually improve itself.</blockquote>If intelligence can be expressed as a short formula (think Maxwell's equations or E = mc<sup>2</sup>), we might not need to make a seed. We will simply have to find that formula. In general, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No-free-lunch_theorem">No-Free-Lunch theorem</a> implies that there must always be scope for improvement, but there are nevertheless some promising paths that I will post about some other time.<br /><br />Related to seed AI is the point where an AI can read and make sense of human text, such as Wikipedia, Principia Mathematica, etc. If we can reach that goal, an AI would quickly acquire superhuman cross-disciplinary knowledge, which in turn would help it to digest ever more advanced text. To get there, a program has to have plenty of common sense that we all take for granted. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyc">Cyc</a> is an ambitious, long-running, project that tries to collect all this "common sense".<br /><br />A superintelligent AI would be incredibly useful. Useful beyond your wildest fantasies. <sing>.<br /><br />A more intelligent program is likely harder to improve, but at the same time a more intelligent program is better at improving, so we can have reasonable hope for the improvement process to continue indefinitely (or perhaps converge to a single point - the formula for intelligence), although it is hard to guess what the improvement curve will look like. Will the difficulty increase much faster than the capacity? No one knows. It is tempting to make an analogy with humans and note how hard it is for us to rewire the brain to make us fundamentally more intelligent. For most programs this is probably very different. A program is made to be modified, it is software and not, as our brains, firmware or wetware.<br /><br />If we want to talk about improving programs, <span style="font-weight: bold;">we have to define what it means to improve one's intelligence, and thus what it means to be intelligent</span>. We want intelligent systems to be useful. Useful intelligence is, just as science, about <span style="font-style: italic;">prediction, planning and pattern recognition</span>. These are all so intertwined as to be more or less the same thing.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Prediction<br /><br /></span>Given certain input we want to predict what the outcome might be. It is nice if this prediction involves not only the most likely outcome, but also estimates of the probabilities of all the possible outcomes. Even better is if the predictor gives an indication for how certain it is about the probabilities.<br /><br />If I roll a regular dice, I am fairly sure that the probability of a 3 showing up is about 16.7%, of course the dice might be damaged or otherwise unfair, or perhaps I miscalculated 1 / 6 or misunderstand the laws of probability, etc. Neverthless, I am fairly certain. On the other hand, I estimate the probability of Sweden beating Brazil the next time they meet in soccer to about 10%, but I am fairly uncertain about that figure. Thus I should be cautious about acting on it, for example not taking bets. I am, however, quite certain that I am uncertain about my last probability estimation. It is probably not very useful to continue this recursion further, neither for me nor for a program, so I'll be quite satisfied if my AI knows certainties concerning probabilities, but not certainties about certainties.<br /><br />Two classic examples where prediction is useful are weather forecasts and the stock market.<br /><br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Planning</span><br /><br />Prediction is closely related to planning. One way of formalizing planning is to make an enormous tree, where each choice I can make is a branching point and every consequence along with it's probability is also a branching point. In a complex world most of my millions of choices/actions will not have any bearing on me reaching a specific goal, so the tree gets unfeasibly large. The first step is to quickly <span style="font-weight: bold;font-size:100%;" >predict</span><span style="font-size:100%;"> which paths might actually have a significance towards me reaching my goal, thus pruning the tree. Then I have to </span><span style="font-weight: bold;font-size:100%;" >predict</span><span style="font-size:100%;"> what the consequences of my actions are likely to be, making a model of the outside world. Now I have a tree where I can start searching for a solution, in other words make a plan<br /><br />A classic example of a planning problem is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Towers_of_Hanoi">Towers of Hanoi</a>. It is trivially easy to make a program that solves Towers of Hanoi, but it is harder to construct a general AI that, given the rules to the game, solves it in general. You cannot just exhaustively search your decision tree, because Towers of Hanoi with 30 discs requires 2^30 - 1= 1073741823 moves to complete. This means that the depth of the tree is 10^9 and, given at least two paths on each level, 2^(10^9) nodes. That amounts to more than a 1 followed by 300 million zeroes - a ridiculously large number. The planner must reason about the effects of the rules and <span style="font-style: italic;">recognize the pattern</span> for moving the discs.<br /><br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Pattern recognition<br /></span><br />Recognizing patterns is, among other things, the useful property of being able to spot that given <span style="font-style: italic;">this</span>, <span style="font-style: italic;">that</span> follows more/less frequently. A neat way of deciding if you have spotted a pattern is to invoke <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_description_length">Minimum Description Length</a> or MDL. 10101010101010... can be described with the exact digits, or as a repeating pattern of 10s or as alternating 1 and 0. Which one is chosen depends on what language you have chosen to express your pattern in. For longer patterns it makes less and less difference what language you chose. The same reasoning applies to, for example, a picture. If we have a completely black 1000 x 1000 pixel square with a white 500 pixel (in diameter) circle in the middle , then that description is much shorter than actually encoding the image pixel for pixel. We have recognized a pattern.<br /><br />Notice the close relationship between pattern recognition and compression.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Intelligence test<br /></span><br />Constructing a true intelligence test, that can be executed reasonably fast, would be very useful in the research of general AI. You have to be careful when designing such a test, because if it is too simple you will end up with an AI that is specialized on solving exactly your test and nothing else.<br /><br />If we had such a test, a fairly simple, but very interesting, experiment could be made.<br /></span></sing><ol><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Start with a program that produces random output. The seed!</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Measure its intelligence. This producer of random noise is now your first and most intelligent program.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Interpret the currently best program's output as new programs and measure the intelligence of these programs, give this intelligence as feedback to the generating program.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Whenever a program that is more intelligent than the previous most intelligent program is found, use it as the new generator to search for even more intelligent programs.</span></li></ol><span style="font-size:100%;">You might need to add some precautions so that you do not enter an evolutionary dead end, for example by letting different promising generators run in parallell, but the above points are the basic gist of it. This will let you find out how much more time it takes for each successively more intelligent program to construct an even more intelligent program. If you are very, very, lucky and have constructed your intelligence test very well, this might even suffice as the Seed.<br /><br />In coming posts I will describe what the mathematically perfect predictor looks like and what the mathematically perfect planner looks like. They are, at least on the surface, surprisingly dissimilar.<br /></span></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>cognomad</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for the comment on my knol, David!<BR/>You&#39;re right, it sounds very similar on a high level, &amp; I am sure there are many people who&#39;d agree with the definition. But I don&#39;t know of anyone who used it to derive a universal, low-level, quantitative criterion to select inputs &amp; algorithms. The key is to start from the beginning: raw sensory inputs, &amp; &quot;test&quot; their predictive value, in the process discovering more &amp; more complex patterns. That&#39;s what scalability is all about, if you can&#39;t evaluate pixels, it&#39;ll be super-exponentially more difficult to start from more complex data. That&#39;s why I think Cyc, NLP, &amp; high-level approaches in general are hopeless for AGI.<BR/>I am sorry, but your &quot;Intelligence test&quot; idea, besides it being entirely hypothetical &amp; presumably externally administered, has it exactly backwards. Just like many Algorithmic Learning approaches, you want to generate patterns &amp; algorithms, instead of discovering them in a real world. Quite simply, we predict from experience, these patterns &amp; algorithms will have *no* predictive value beyond mere chance, unless they&#39;re derived from the experience. Notice that the difference between patterns &amp; algorithms is strictly in their origin: the former are discovered &amp; the later are &quot;invented&quot;.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
