<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: compression | IFHO]]></title>
  <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/categories/compression/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fendrich.se/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-23T11:45:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://fendrich.se/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Fendrich]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Compression, prediction and artificial intelligence]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2010/12/28/compression-prediction-and-artificial/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2010/12/28/compression-prediction-and-artificial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Compression is one of the most powerful concepts in computing. For the normal computer user, compression is associated with making files smaller, so you can store more of them or send them faster over the Internet, but there is much more to it.<br /><br />An optimal compressor can (or could, if it existed) be used for prediction of the future of a sequence of events (weather, sports, stocks, political events, etc), for example by trying all possible continuations and examine how well it compresses given the history. Conversely, an optimal predictor that gives the correct probability of each possible next symbol can be used for optimal compression by using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/arithmetic_coding">arithmetic coding</a>.<br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;"><br /></span><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Compression and prediction</span><br /><br /><i>This section on background theory contains possibly scary math and dense prose, but should be understandable for most programmers. Maybe re-read the sentences a couple of times.</i><br /><br />Ray Solomonoff has shown&nbsp;<a href="http://www.theworld.com/~rjs/chris1.pdf">[PDF]</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;that if we let Sk be the infinite set of all programs for a machine M, such that M(Sk) gives an output with X as prefix (i.e the first bits of the output is X), then the probability of X becomes the sum of the probabilities of all of its programs, where the probability of a program is&nbsp;2 ** (-|Sk|) if |Sk| is the length of the program in bits and "**" means "to the power of". As X gets longer, the error of the predictions approach zero, if the error is calculated as the total squared probability difference.<br /><br />A technicality is that only those programs count, that does not still produce X, when the last bit of the program is removed.<br /><br />To give a slightly more concrete example, say that you have a sequence of events - a history - and encode those as a sequence of symbols, X. Let us further say that you have a machine, M, that can read a program S and output a sequence of symbols. If you have no further information on your sequence of events, then the best estimate for the probability of a symbol Z to occur next (i.e the best prediction) is given by the set of all programs that output your history X followed by Z. Programs which output X+Z and are short are weighted higher (the 2 ** (-|Sk|) part).<br /><br /><br /><div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;">Even more concretely, given the binary sequence 101010101, you wonder what the probability is that the next bit will be 0 given that you know nothing else of this sequence. Sum 2 ** (-program length) for all programs that output 1010101010 vs those that output 1010101011 as their first bits (they are allowed to continue outputting stuff). If we call these sums sum0 and sum1 respectively, then the probability of 0 coming next is sum0 / (sum0 + sum1) and the probability of 1 coming next is sum1 / (sum0 + sum1).</div><br /><br />Obviously you cannot find all these programs by just trying every possible program, because 1) they are infinitely many and 2) given <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halting_problem">the halting problem</a> you cannot in general know if a running program is in an infinite loop or if it will eventually output X.<br /><br />There is an area of probability theory called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_description_length">Minimum description length</a>, where the language is chosen to be so simple (not Turing complete) so that you can actually find the shortest program or "description". Calculating probabilities this way is very similar to Bayesian probability, but more general.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Solomonoff in (almost) practice</span><br /><br />Although the point of the theorem is not to apply it directly in practice, for short sequences X we can actually try. We can avoid problem 1 above, there are infinitely many programs, by generating random programs and see if they produce X. If they do, we count them. This way we can produce an approximation of what the true sum0 and sum1 are. If we set up our random generation such that shorter programs are more likely, then we don't have to bother with the 2 ** (-program length) part and may just have a running count for each sum. If the sequence is too long, this method will be impractical since almost no randomly generated programs will actually output X.<br /><br />Problem 2 above, when we test programs they may not halt, is harder, but Levin has proposed a way around it. If we in addition to program length use running time (number of instructions executed) as a measure of the probability of our program, we can start by generating all the programs that we intend to test and then run them all in parallel. As our execution moves forward, we will get an increasingly accurate approximation of the true sum0 and sum1, without getting stuck on infinite loops.<br /><br />If we want to get even more practical, it can be shown that the shortest program that produces X will generally dominate the others and thus it will predict the most likely next symbol. That way you can just search for programs that output X and the currently shortest program will be your best guess. Since we no longer care about the relative probability of the next symbol, but only which is most likely, the search does not have to be random. Thus we can use any method we like for finding a short program. If you search for programs that produce X and find one that almost does, you can construct a "true" solution from that one, by constructing a prefix part that hard codes the places where your original program is wrong. This will produce a longer program, where the length, and thus the "score", is the length of the prefix + the length of your faulty solution. The size of the shortest program that outputs X is called the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kolmogorov_complexity">Kolmogorov complexity</a> of X. The size of the shortest program that outputs X, measured in program size + log(running time), is called the <a href="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Algorithmic_complexity">Levin complexity</a> of X.<br /><br />One way to find these programs is to use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_programming">genetic programming</a>, just take care that you don't think that you can count the number of programs that produce X and get relative probabilities, because your search will now be skewed towards the solution (and thus its prediction) that you find first.<br /><br />A small problem is that depending on what machine you choose, i.e which instructions your programs can use and the length of these instructions, you will get different results. The method has a built in bias, since there is no one correct Turing complete language. This difference will however be smaller as X gets longer. One way to understand that is to note that any Turing complete language can emulate any other Turing complete language and that the size of such an emulator is finite. This is called the compiler theorem.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Compression is understanding and the Hutter Prize</span><br /><br />When we understand something, we can describe it succinctly. If I have an image of a red perfect circle, the size will be much larger if I describe the individual pixels rather than just say "a red circle of diameter d and thickness t". When I understand what the image is depicting, I can describe it shorter. Sometimes a lossy compression of observed data will actually express the truth better than the exact data. If I take a photo of a red circle, the photo will probably not be perfect, but if I notice what the photo is showing, I can compress it as "a red circle" and some noise which I throw away, and suddenly my lossy compression is a better depiction of the truth.<br /><br />This equivalence between compression and general intelligence led Marcus Hutter to announce the <a href="http://prize.hutter1.net/">Hutter Prize</a>, where money is awarded for the best compression of 100 megabyte of English Wikipedia articles. So far the compression algorithms have been impressive (compressing the text to about 15%), but not shown much intelligence or understanding of the articles. When they do start to exhibit some understanding, I think that if they are allowed to compress the data in a slightly lossy way, the first thing that will happen is that some spelling and layout mistakes will be corrected, because these will be surprising to the compressor and thus demand an unusually long representation.<br /><br />Matt Mahoney has written a good rationale on the Hutter Prize <a href="http://cs.fit.edu/~mmahoney/compression/rationale.html">here</a>.<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Compression in practice - the juicy stuff</span><br /><br />Compression is a powerful tool to measure success and avoid overfitting in a variety of common AI problems. The methods I laid out here are interesting mostly from a theoretical perspective, because of their prohibitively long running times.&nbsp;In my next post, I will expand on my thoughts on how you can use these results to get actual, practical algorithms for common AI problems.<br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;"><br /></span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seed AI]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/08/30/seed-ai/"/>
    <updated>2007-08-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/08/30/seed-ai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<span style="font-size:130%;">Le grand assumption<br /><br /></span>The assumption of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seed_AI">seed AI</a> is this: <blockquote>If we can make a program intelligent enough, a "seed" of intelligence, we can also make it gradually improve itself.</blockquote>If intelligence can be expressed as a short formula (think Maxwell's equations or E = mc<sup>2</sup>), we might not need to make a seed. We will simply have to find that formula. In general, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No-free-lunch_theorem">No-Free-Lunch theorem</a> implies that there must always be scope for improvement, but there are nevertheless some promising paths that I will post about some other time.<br /><br />Related to seed AI is the point where an AI can read and make sense of human text, such as Wikipedia, Principia Mathematica, etc. If we can reach that goal, an AI would quickly acquire superhuman cross-disciplinary knowledge, which in turn would help it to digest ever more advanced text. To get there, a program has to have plenty of common sense that we all take for granted. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyc">Cyc</a> is an ambitious, long-running, project that tries to collect all this "common sense".<br /><br />A superintelligent AI would be incredibly useful. Useful beyond your wildest fantasies. <sing>.<br /><br />A more intelligent program is likely harder to improve, but at the same time a more intelligent program is better at improving, so we can have reasonable hope for the improvement process to continue indefinitely (or perhaps converge to a single point - the formula for intelligence), although it is hard to guess what the improvement curve will look like. Will the difficulty increase much faster than the capacity? No one knows. It is tempting to make an analogy with humans and note how hard it is for us to rewire the brain to make us fundamentally more intelligent. For most programs this is probably very different. A program is made to be modified, it is software and not, as our brains, firmware or wetware.<br /><br />If we want to talk about improving programs, <span style="font-weight: bold;">we have to define what it means to improve one's intelligence, and thus what it means to be intelligent</span>. We want intelligent systems to be useful. Useful intelligence is, just as science, about <span style="font-style: italic;">prediction, planning and pattern recognition</span>. These are all so intertwined as to be more or less the same thing.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Prediction<br /><br /></span>Given certain input we want to predict what the outcome might be. It is nice if this prediction involves not only the most likely outcome, but also estimates of the probabilities of all the possible outcomes. Even better is if the predictor gives an indication for how certain it is about the probabilities.<br /><br />If I roll a regular dice, I am fairly sure that the probability of a 3 showing up is about 16.7%, of course the dice might be damaged or otherwise unfair, or perhaps I miscalculated 1 / 6 or misunderstand the laws of probability, etc. Neverthless, I am fairly certain. On the other hand, I estimate the probability of Sweden beating Brazil the next time they meet in soccer to about 10%, but I am fairly uncertain about that figure. Thus I should be cautious about acting on it, for example not taking bets. I am, however, quite certain that I am uncertain about my last probability estimation. It is probably not very useful to continue this recursion further, neither for me nor for a program, so I'll be quite satisfied if my AI knows certainties concerning probabilities, but not certainties about certainties.<br /><br />Two classic examples where prediction is useful are weather forecasts and the stock market.<br /><br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Planning</span><br /><br />Prediction is closely related to planning. One way of formalizing planning is to make an enormous tree, where each choice I can make is a branching point and every consequence along with it's probability is also a branching point. In a complex world most of my millions of choices/actions will not have any bearing on me reaching a specific goal, so the tree gets unfeasibly large. The first step is to quickly <span style="font-weight: bold;font-size:100%;" >predict</span><span style="font-size:100%;"> which paths might actually have a significance towards me reaching my goal, thus pruning the tree. Then I have to </span><span style="font-weight: bold;font-size:100%;" >predict</span><span style="font-size:100%;"> what the consequences of my actions are likely to be, making a model of the outside world. Now I have a tree where I can start searching for a solution, in other words make a plan<br /><br />A classic example of a planning problem is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Towers_of_Hanoi">Towers of Hanoi</a>. It is trivially easy to make a program that solves Towers of Hanoi, but it is harder to construct a general AI that, given the rules to the game, solves it in general. You cannot just exhaustively search your decision tree, because Towers of Hanoi with 30 discs requires 2^30 - 1= 1073741823 moves to complete. This means that the depth of the tree is 10^9 and, given at least two paths on each level, 2^(10^9) nodes. That amounts to more than a 1 followed by 300 million zeroes - a ridiculously large number. The planner must reason about the effects of the rules and <span style="font-style: italic;">recognize the pattern</span> for moving the discs.<br /><br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Pattern recognition<br /></span><br />Recognizing patterns is, among other things, the useful property of being able to spot that given <span style="font-style: italic;">this</span>, <span style="font-style: italic;">that</span> follows more/less frequently. A neat way of deciding if you have spotted a pattern is to invoke <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_description_length">Minimum Description Length</a> or MDL. 10101010101010... can be described with the exact digits, or as a repeating pattern of 10s or as alternating 1 and 0. Which one is chosen depends on what language you have chosen to express your pattern in. For longer patterns it makes less and less difference what language you chose. The same reasoning applies to, for example, a picture. If we have a completely black 1000 x 1000 pixel square with a white 500 pixel (in diameter) circle in the middle , then that description is much shorter than actually encoding the image pixel for pixel. We have recognized a pattern.<br /><br />Notice the close relationship between pattern recognition and compression.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Intelligence test<br /></span><br />Constructing a true intelligence test, that can be executed reasonably fast, would be very useful in the research of general AI. You have to be careful when designing such a test, because if it is too simple you will end up with an AI that is specialized on solving exactly your test and nothing else.<br /><br />If we had such a test, a fairly simple, but very interesting, experiment could be made.<br /></span></sing><ol><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Start with a program that produces random output. The seed!</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Measure its intelligence. This producer of random noise is now your first and most intelligent program.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Interpret the currently best program's output as new programs and measure the intelligence of these programs, give this intelligence as feedback to the generating program.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Whenever a program that is more intelligent than the previous most intelligent program is found, use it as the new generator to search for even more intelligent programs.</span></li></ol><span style="font-size:100%;">You might need to add some precautions so that you do not enter an evolutionary dead end, for example by letting different promising generators run in parallell, but the above points are the basic gist of it. This will let you find out how much more time it takes for each successively more intelligent program to construct an even more intelligent program. If you are very, very, lucky and have constructed your intelligence test very well, this might even suffice as the Seed.<br /><br />In coming posts I will describe what the mathematically perfect predictor looks like and what the mathematically perfect planner looks like. They are, at least on the surface, surprisingly dissimilar.<br /></span></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>cognomad</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for the comment on my knol, David!<BR/>You&#39;re right, it sounds very similar on a high level, &amp; I am sure there are many people who&#39;d agree with the definition. But I don&#39;t know of anyone who used it to derive a universal, low-level, quantitative criterion to select inputs &amp; algorithms. The key is to start from the beginning: raw sensory inputs, &amp; &quot;test&quot; their predictive value, in the process discovering more &amp; more complex patterns. That&#39;s what scalability is all about, if you can&#39;t evaluate pixels, it&#39;ll be super-exponentially more difficult to start from more complex data. That&#39;s why I think Cyc, NLP, &amp; high-level approaches in general are hopeless for AGI.<BR/>I am sorry, but your &quot;Intelligence test&quot; idea, besides it being entirely hypothetical &amp; presumably externally administered, has it exactly backwards. Just like many Algorithmic Learning approaches, you want to generate patterns &amp; algorithms, instead of discovering them in a real world. Quite simply, we predict from experience, these patterns &amp; algorithms will have *no* predictive value beyond mere chance, unless they&#39;re derived from the experience. Notice that the difference between patterns &amp; algorithms is strictly in their origin: the former are discovered &amp; the later are &quot;invented&quot;.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
