<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: solitaire | IFHO]]></title>
  <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/categories/solitaire/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fendrich.se/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-26T14:45:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://fendrich.se/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Fendrich]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why planning is hard]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/21/why-planning-is-hard/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/21/why-planning-is-hard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
After my last post about planning I thought some more on the issue and had something close to an epiphany.<br /><br />When you plan, in the solitaire sense, you need rules governing what moves are legal - transformation rules. If you treat these rules like black boxes, just understanding them by playing around with positions and see how they behave, you can only do so much. An important rule might be usable extremely rarely, but nevertheless be the key to success if you specifically aim to reach a position where it is applicable. This means that you might miss how important a rule (or an exception to a rule) is, when just "black-boxing" it, because it's usefulness or purpose might never come up.<br /><br />Even if you have no such rare rules in your system, the best you can hope for if you want to analyze a system when black-boxing is just to formulate your own internal rules for how the system seems to behave.<br /><br />Thus, <span style="font-weight: bold;">the reason planning is hard is that you need to be able to analyze/understand code to understand transformation rules in general</span> and understanding code is hard. You need to understand when you may take actions and what these actions do, i.e understand transformation rules, whatever system you are planning for.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">A small prediction<br /><br /></span>The reason why good planning is a key to analyze code and prove things in formal systems is that you need to understand code in order to plan. Thus, I postulate, when something can analyze code better than I, it will quickly learn to do everything else intelligence-based better than I. The implication probably works both ways, so the first program that is thoroughly smarter than I will most likely have it's foundation laid upon the ability to reason about code.</div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Home Broker</div>
<div class='content'>
Hello. This post is likeable, and your blog is very interesting, congratulations :-). I will add in my blogroll =). If possible gives a last there on my blog, it is about the <A HREF="http://home-broker-brasil.blogspot.com" REL="nofollow">Home Broker</A>, I hope you enjoy. The address is http://home-broker-brasil.blogspot.com. A hug.<A HREF="8250556117" REL="nofollow"></A></div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deceptively simple game]]></title>
    <link href="http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/12/deceptively-simple-game/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fendrich.se/blog/2007/12/12/deceptively-simple-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I would pay a handsome sum (say $1 million, if I could raise it) for a program that could do the following well-defined, seemingly simple, task.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">General solitaire solver</span><br /><br />Take as input a list of rules for a solitaire-like game. The rules are deterministic transformation rules, defining which moves are legal given a certain position. The rules will be given in whatever Turing complete language the solver likes. For example a simple Scheme dialect without side-effects or a subset of x86 machine code.<br /><br />As long as it solves the task, the solver is free to treat the rules as <span style="font-style: italic;">black boxes</span> that take one position and outputs a, possibly empty, list of potential positions.<br /><br />The solver will then take an initial position as second input and one or more target positions as final input. In fact, to make it more general, take a function that tells whether a position is the target or not.<br /><br />As output, I want a sequence of transformations that leads from the initial position to a target. It does not have to be the shortest sequence, just a sequence. Also I want the answer reasonably fast. At least as fast as I could solve it myself.<br /><br /><span style="font-size:130%;">Extra features</span><br /><br />While I would be very happy with just the above, here are some extra features that would be nice.<br /><br /><ul><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Instead of a binary target function, let me use a continuous target function, and give as output a sequence that gives an end position with as good a score as possible.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Accept one or more opponents. This would be useful for playing games - go, shogi, chess, etc, but apart from that would probably be a step towards the stochastic thing below.</span></li><li><span style="font-size:100%;">Allow the transformation rules to behave in a stochastic/probabilistic manner.</span></li></ul><span style="font-size:130%;">Why?</span><br /><br />I have no particular desire to solve solitaire automatically, so why would I want a generalized solitaire solver? Well, if you can input the rules for solitaire, you can also input the rules for <a href="http://seedai.blogspot.com/search/label/Towers%20of%20Hanoi">Towers of Hanoi</a>, which I used as an example of difficult planning in another post. Suddenly you can solve a whole range of reasoning problems, mathematical proofs, reasoning about programs and all sorts of interesting and important stuff.<br /><br />It is interesting to think about the problem from the point of view of solving solitaire or some other simple one-man game. I think it makes it less intimidating.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
